First of all, I have to slightly correct myself:
I said in the previous video that I finished
last lecture week with the slide on moving
if-then-else expressions in and out of function
argument positions.
That wasn't actually true.
That was slide 47, whereas last week's lectures
ended with slide 52.
So, there was some other material afterwards,
namely, talking about syntax.
That said, I want to call out another observation
from the exercises here.
Actually, this is not exactly from this year's
exercise tasks, but from a task similar to
the "moving sun" example, from last year.
There was some observation that I want to
make here again, even though it's not exactly
the example that was used in this year's exercises.
It's about common subexpressions.
So, it appears here in the case of an if-then-else,
but that's not the main point.
The point is about common subexpressions.
Also Marcellus and Oliver talked about this
in their videos, about moving expressions
that appear repeatedly, to somehow named entities.
And that was used there for the grass, for
the sun, for branches, etc.
So, basically for constant expressions.
But the concept of common subexpression elimination
applies also to expressions that contain variables.
And this is nicely illustrated here.
Let's consider this example.
There was some "scene" computation and somehow
it had something to do with rotation or moving
stuff around.
So, there was some condition: if 8 * sin t
> 0 then do something (where sin and cos are
used), and else do something else.
This doesn't really matter.
Maybe this was blank here.
Maybe something else.
The important thing here is that there was
a recomputation.
So, this value is computed here, and then at
least if it is positive, the "then" branch
is taken, and it is computed again.
It's not a very expensive computation.
Yes, just computing the sine may not be the
most problematic case, but it would be both
more efficient and also clearer to say: Let's
give names to these things.
We can simply name things that contain no
other variables, but of course, we can also
name the subexpressions "8 * cos t" and "8
* sin t".
And then it becomes clearer because then
we can see that we actually check if the y-coordinate
is greater than zero, then we move whatever
we had here to the x and y position, otherwise
we do something else.
So, this is both clearer (the second version),
and also slightly more efficient.
Because we don't compute this very same mathematical
expression twice.
There is a concern that sometimes comes up
at this point, maybe also the reason why the
student originally writing this code didn't
do this renaming, that well, maybe in the
"else" branch we don't need the cosine (the
x value).
So, here we say: If this condition is true,
then we compute this, and then we have to
compute this a second time.
But if this condition is false, we go to the
"else" branch.
And maybe in the "else" branch we don't have
the cosine or the sine.
Maybe the "else" branch is really "blank".
Then one could argue that while here we compute
the x and the y, and then we check whether
the y is positive (if so, then of course we
use the x and y), and otherwise we do nothing
(we have the "blank"); then why do we have
the computation of x?
That is a concern that students might have
or have had at this point.
And well, this concern is unfounded.
Why?
Because we are not in an imperative language.
So, it's not even true that at this point we
compute x and y.
It's not a variable assignment.
It is not like you go through this piece of
code, and you compute this value, assign it
to x, compute this value, assign it to y,
do the check, and if we end up in the "else"
branch, and have a "blank", then we have computed
the x for nothing.
That's not what's happening here because
this is not sequential code by which we compute
this, and this, and this.
These are just mathematical definitions.
So, what this is saying is that x, if you
happen to need it later on, will be evaluated
using this expression.
So, it is not computing the x at all yet, just
declaring: If x is relevant at some point,
then that's what the value would be.
And the same goes for y.
Then, we check the y, of course.
The y will indeed be computed, but isn't computed
at this point when it is declared.
It's computed when this check happens.
And of course, we need the value of y in order
to do this comparison.
So, the y will be computed when we do this
check.
If this check is positive, then we will do
this, and then of course, we will need the
x.
And that's when the x would be computed.
So then that's when the cos t will be computed
here.
If, however, the y turns out to not be positive,
we end up in the "else" branch.
The "else" branch is "blank", for example.
So, it doesn't even mention x.
Then x will never be computed.
So, you have to free yourself from sequential
thinking, where seeing this, you think: Now
I compute the expensive x, and now I compute
the expensive y, and then I do something with
those values.
That's not what's happening, because this
is not sequential code.
It's mathematical declarations.
And if the x is not needed because in the
"else" branch we have "blank", then the x
will never be computed.
Let's talk a bit about types.
And first of all, about number types.
That is also something that is now increasingly
coming up in the exercises.
The first examples in CodeWorld, of course,
were all about Doubles, because that's the
unit in which things are measured in CodeWorld.
Then, in the last exercise task, about the
list of natural numbers, there was already
this integer type for non-fractional values (whole numbers).
And actually, some students already mixed
floating-point and integer types in that exercise.
It was not needed.
There was a way to compute this just on integers.
But some students tried to used conversion
for detecting the number of digits of a number.
Instead of working with division and rounding
of values, etc.
So, they already worked with functions that
move between floating-point and integer values.
You will, at some places, need both and also
their interplay.
So, we have to talk about this.
And it also serves as the first view into
some aspects of the types in Haskell, other
than what you have seen so far in function
types.
First of all, from the outside, Haskell does
have various number types.
Like in most programming languages, there
are integer types of different sizes and there
are floating-point types of different sizes.
So, you see here Float and Double.
They correspond roughly to what you find in
other languages with those type names.
The Rational type is maybe not so common in
other languages.
It's really a type of the rational numbers
with arbitrary precision.
These are not floating-point numbers.
Actually, every rational number is exactly
representable in this type.
So, there is no loss of precision when, for
example, adding rational numbers.
And also, for integers there is this interesting
distinction between Int and Integer.
And the way to think about this is that Int
is basically the machine integer, so something
which has a fixed bit length like 32 or 64
bits.
So, there is a finite range of integer numbers
that can be represented in Int.
Whereas Integer is the mathematical integer
type.
So, these are really arbitrary large integer
numbers, with an arbitrary number of positions
and no loss of precision.
So, we have these different types.
And of course, we can use our literal numbers
with different types, just as in other languages.
So, the number three, just a constant written
3, can be an Int, can be a Float, can be an
Integer, or can be a Rational, or many other
types.
So for a number you don't see, as given, which
type it is.
That is basically polymorphic or overloaded.
There are also constants that don't have all
the number types.
So if you write 3.5, then the compiler knows
(and also we do) that it's not an Int, nor
an Integer.
So, 3.5 could be a Float or a Double, but it
couldn't be an Integer, for example.
Whereas 3 can be both an Integer and a Float.
That's a common practice in other languages
as well.
Also, as expected in some sense, there are
conversion functions.
But we will see that they play a slightly
different role in some situations on the next
slide.
But if we need to convert between some of
these number types, then we can do so.
So, there are conversion functions that don't
lose precision.
These are functions that go from Int to Integer,
or other non-floating-point types to any number
type.
For example, if you want to go from machine
integers to this arbitrary precision integer
type, then you can use the function "fromIntegral".
It is not "fromInteger" or something like
that.
That is something students sometimes mix up.
Because there are also older versions of Haskell
where it is still existing, but not really
used, or mainly deprecated.
There is a "fromInteger" function as well.
It's not something that you should use.
You should use the "fromIntegral" function.
It has many different types.
It is also overloaded.
So, it can convert an Int to an Integer, an
Integer to an Int, an Int to a Rational, and
an Int to a Float/Rational/Double, as I mentioned
already.
So, these are basically from one integer type
into a number type, whether that number type
is an integer type or not.
And there is no loss of precision here.
Well, in the case of "from Integer to Int",
there is some loss of precision, of course.
There must be, because of the limited expressiveness.
But there's no loss of precision in terms
of rounding errors because of digits after
the comma sign or something like that.
Because this just goes from Integer and similar
types.
In the opposite direction, in some sense,
there are functions that really have a rounding
error/discrepancy.
Because if you have 3.5 and you want an integer,
then you have to go to 3 or 4, so you must
make a change.
You can round up, you can round down, you
can truncate.
And basically, for all these different modes,
there are functions in Haskell.
So "truncate" would go from 3.5 to 3, whereas
"round" would move from 3.5 to 4, because
of the rounding up.
And "ceiling" and "floor" are similar to "truncate",
but behave differently depending on whether
they get negative or positive numbers.
Which types do these precision losing conversion
functions have?
They can move from a Float to an Int, for
example.
Because the input would be a floating-point
number, because we have something like 3.5.
The outcome will be, again, an integral type
like Int or Integer.
That's because after you have "truncated",
you have a 3 or a 4.
So, you don't need a floating-point number
anymore.
You can move, with these functions, from this
to an Integer or Int type.
In addition to the constants that are overloaded,
also most of the mathematical operators are
overloaded.
Because it would be very cumbersome and inconvenient
(but actually, it is the case in some languages)
that you need different mathematical operators
depending on whether you work on floating-point
numbers or integer numbers, for example.
There are certain versions like a specific
function for integer division in Haskell,
but most of the operators are overloaded.
So if you have something like f x = 2 * x
+ 3.5, then you don't have to somehow make
your own distinction about 3.5 being a floating-point
number, and about this being an integer number.
In the sense that this may be an integer multiplication,
but then, floating-point additions, so maybe
some conversion would be needed.
No, because these operators are overloaded.
They work at the correct types.
So, in 3 + 4.5 the "+" knows that it must be
a floating-point addition, because we have
a floating-point number here.
It also knows that this 3, even though it
could also be an integer, will actually be
taken as a floating-point 3.
And that's also why this works.
And an appropriate type for f will be chosen
by the compiler if you do something like this.
It will work out that the x must also be a
floating-point value, because otherwise you
couldn't double it and then add it with a
floating-point addition.
Similarly, if you have some other function
which uses f, then again, we know from what
I just said that x (the argument of f) must
be a floating-point thing, because of this
expression.
And that works out nicely because the 4 can
also be seen as a floating-point value.
Then the outcome of the f will also be floating-point
values.
So, the g will actually know that this division
must be a floating-point division, so y must
also be a floating-point number.
So if you write something like this, then
we don't have to convert, because the language
overloads both the constants and the mathematical
operations.
That's the case here, because we leave the
compiler the choice of what types to assign
to x and y.
We haven't written down types for f and g,
and made no constraints on x and y, nor on
the outcome of these functions.
So, the compiler can, via overloading, choose
appropriate number types for x and y.
In this case, it will choose floating-point
types because of what I just explained.
If, on the other hand, we do write down explicit
function types, and those also constrain the
input and output types, for example to integers,
then we need to convert.
To illustrate this, let's look at a similar
example.
First, let's look at this here.
Let's say I want f to be a function from integers
to floats.
Then if I want to use the same expression
as here, I actually have to make sure that
this value in this position is a floating-point
value.
And it isn't.
If I say, f goes from integer to float, then
x would be an integer.
Then in order to use it for floating-point
multiplication, which I have to do because
afterwards I want to do a floating-point addition,
then I have to convert this x from Int to
a floating-point number.
And that's what "fromIntegral" can do, because
as I said on the previous slide, this "fromIntegral"
can go from types like Int or Integer to any
suitable other type.
So, it could go to Float.
So, this will work.
And this is then a kind of conversion.
Yes, it is not a syntactic conversion as happens
in C.
It's a function which does this conversion.
So, it is not somehow a built-in extra syntactic
construct.
And similarly, if for example I do an example
as above:
So, the f x is again free to choose its type,
but somehow in the second function, instead
of putting the value 4 here, I want to have
the length of the string "abcd".
Now I would have to know that the length-function
in Haskell is a function which takes, in this
case, a String, and gives a natural number.
It doesn't give a floating-point number, because
"length" makes more sense with an integer
result.
So if I write something like this (so I replace
the 4 by the length of "abcd"), then again
I need to convert.
Why?
Because here, the 4 didn't have a type, so
the compiler decided, via overloading: "Well,
I consider this 4 to be a floating-point number".
This can't be done here if I say it is the
result of the length-function.
The length-function always returns an integer.
If I then want to use it as an argument to
f, and for f the compiler has deduced that
the argument must be a floating-point value
because of this addition here, then I need
to make sure that I embed my integer (which
comes out of the length-function) into this
floating-point type.
And again, I can do this with "fromIntegral".
So, I would again need a conversion here.
Now, at this point, students sometimes ask:
"Why is it that here I have to make these
explicit conversions, whereas here they are
somehow hidden? Maybe the compiler is introducing
silent conversions here."
But that's not how to view this.
It is not the case that here we have explicit
conversions, and here we have somehow hidden
conversions.
No.
What's actually happening is:
Here we need conversions, here we don't need
conversions.
So, there are no hidden conversions.
Just by not giving types for f and g, we let
the compiler choose what the types are.
And the compiler can, in this case, choose
the types in such a way that no conversions
are necessary.
Because the compiler simply decides that x
is a Float.
Then there is no need for conversion.
If we say "No, the x is an integer", then
conversion is necessary.
And the compiler won't introduce conversion
on its own.
We have to write it.
Otherwise, it would defeat the discipline
of types in Haskell (also for number types).
For the sake of completeness: There actually
are some operators that are not completely
overloaded.
So, they are not available at all types.
And division is one of these examples.
The division symbol, as you are probably used
to see it in many languages, like this, is
not available on integer types.
It is a floating-point style operation.
It does work on the rationals, but not on
integer types.
What do we have instead?
We have a dedicated division function.
This operator "div" is also known from other
languages.
It operates on Int or Integer, but not on
floating-point numbers, for example.
So, it is really a different operation, a
different symbol than the slash symbol for
division on floating-point numbers.
A nice syntactical trick is that binary functions
like "div", but also all non-arithmetic functions,
can be used like operators.
So while there is no slash operator for division
in Haskell, this function can be used as an
operator by simply writing it infix and with
these backticks.
But that's just syntactic sugar.
So for "17 `div` 3", written this way, the
compiler knows that it is the same as applying
the binary function "div" to 17 and 3 as its
two arguments.
It is just a different way of writing it.
It is not a new operator or something like
that.
And another useful thing, of course, is that
many further mathematical constants and functions
exist.
We have seen some of them already.
I used the mathematical constant pi.
I used this sine function.
There also is this function for square root;
minimum and maximum functions on integers
and other types.
So, a lot of functions exist and have the expected
names, similar to mathematical libraries in
other languages.
I won't introduce all of them, they will simply
come up in examples.
So if you find a need, then maybe look up
in some Haskell library or the standard library
what the function is that you need for a certain
purpose.
So, I will not give a complete list or something
like that.
That shouldn't be needed.
Still in the context of number types, let
me also make an observation based on past
years' exercises.
So, this is also something that probably will
come up again in exercise tasks now.
I mentioned the need for conversion.
And the general strategy to deal with that
in your next exercise tasks, where you might
encounter both integer and floating-point
types, is that usually it doesn't hurt to
add some "fromIntegral" calls.
Why is that?
They may have many different types.
So, among others, they have types
like "Int → Int".
So if you have something which maybe draws
from a generator list in a list comprehension,
0 to 10 or something like that:
It would be an Int, but maybe you need to
use it as a Double.
Then it doesn't hurt to add a "fromIntegral"
on the variable that you draw from that "0
to 10" list.
Because either it will be used as an Int,
and that's fine, because "fromIntegral" will
turn Int into Int (nothing has changed), or
it will be used as a Double, and then you
are also fine, because you have added this
"fromIntegral" call, which will actually turn
the integer into a Double, for example.
In that sense, "fromIntegral" in the worst case
will be a no-op.
So, it doesn't really hurt to add it at certain
places, in particular, if you get error messages
about Int vs. Double, for example.
Also, if you add redundant fromIntegral calls,
actually the compiler/Autotool will warn you
about this.
So, in that sense, it doesn't hurt.
It is similar to the brackets.
In the beginning, when you write Haskell programs
you tend to add too many brackets, and maybe
it is even a good strategy at the beginning
to add a few more brackets just to be on the
safe side, and then let the compiler or Autotool
or whatever tool you use tell you which brackets
are redundant.
In a similar way, you could use this fromIntegral,
add it where you are suspicious that you might
need it, and if in your final program it turns
out it's not needed, then you can have the
compiler or Autotool tell you where you can
remove some of these "fromIntegral" calls again.
That's then a safe strategy.
That was one remark.
Another remark generally applies to all functions,
but specifically (because of all these conversion
issues) to types involving numbers.
It's good practice and really helpful to write
down type signatures, at least for the top-level
functions.
This has benefits like the compiler being
better able to help you with type errors.
But among other things, it saves you from
dealing with certain complicated looking types
like the one here.
So if you write some function on numbers, and
you don't say "I want this to be a function from Float
to Float",
then the compiler will infer some type.
It might infer something which looks somewhat
daunting like this "Floating a" and "Ord a",
and then this strange arrow which isn't a
function arrow, and then "a → a".
At the moment, you are not expected to understand
this.
If you want to have some inkling of what's
happening here: it's a bit similar to Java
interfaces, where "Floating" and "Ord" are basically
completely abstract classes (in Java, they would be
declared with "interface").
But you don't need this at this point.
And you can avoid such concepts in Haskell
by being more explicit.
So, if you write down that your "fun" is a
function from Int to Int, then the compiler
will believe you.
Well, it will not simply believe you, it will
check it.
And you don't have to rely on inference which
might lead to such complicated looking types.
So, this is a comment specifically about number
types.
But also more generally, at least top-level
functions in your exercise submissions should
be given type signatures.
You don't have to do it for all the local
definitions, like I did in the example earlier
today with the local functions x and y.
You don't have to write all the type signatures
for things like this, but for top-level functions
you should prefer to do it.
Of course, there are not just number types.
There are all kinds of types in Haskell.
And I will talk through some basic types on
this slide and probably afterwards make a
small video with the whiteboard to look at
some example values, in particular, for compound
types.
So, let's go through the pre-existing types
quickly, besides numbers.
So, there is a type of Boolean values.
And actually the only inhabitants of that
type are "True" and "False".
And on those values, you have operators like
"&&" (and), "||" (or), "not".
So, the logical operators on the Boolean type.
It is really a separate type.
It is not like in C, where somehow 0 and 1
of an integer type also act as Boolean values.
That is really a separate type: True and False,
and operators on them.
And of course, this type is actually also
the type of conditions you use in "if-then-else".
The condition must be something that evaluates
to a "Bool".
And also of course, you can use these Boolean
operators in these places.
So, this is one thing.
And then, there is a type of character values.
It is called "Char".
It has the expected values, like all the letters
that you can have, also special characters
like "a new line" ('\n'), etc.
There are operations like moving forwards
of backwards in the ASCII table, in a sense.
The successor of 'a' is 'b', and the predecessor
of 'b' as a character is 'a'.
You can also compare characters with the usual
comparison operations that you would also
use on numbers.
So, these are also overloaded.
More interestingly, there is a construction
of list types.
We have already seen some lists, namely when
we did list comprehensions: lists of pictures.
But this construction can be used arbitrarily.
So, you can have a list of anything.
You can have a list of integers.
You can have a list of Bools.
You can have a list of lists of integers.
And there are many predefined functions.
You see some of them later on, or maybe next
week.
But anyway, there is a lot of available machinery
to work on list, such as the list comprehensions,
but also defining functions and operators.
So, you have, for example, the "reverse" function
which takes a list, reverses the order.
Or functions for selecting certain parts of
a list, the prefix or suffix, or whatever.
And: lists are homogeneous.
So, if you have a list of Ints (integers),
then in that list you can only have Int (integer)
numbers.
We can't have a list where some of the values
are integers and some of them are Boolean
values.
You have a type of integer (Int) lists.
You have a type of Boolean (Bool) lists.
But you don't have a type of "some of these
values are integers, and some are Booleans".
So, this has to be homogeneous.
Then there is a type of character sequences,
and it is called "String" as in other languages.
But it is a list of characters.
Yes, we can write a special notation ("abc"),
but what it really is under the hood, it is
a normal list, where the element type is the
character type (Char).
So "abc" is actually the list of these three
characters 'a', 'b' and 'c'.
So, something like the "reverse" function I
just mentioned is also applicable on strings,
because strings are also just lists.
It just happens to be the case that it's a
list of characters.
Important in this connection is that in CodeWorld,
this String type is not directly used.
So CodeWorld uses its own text type.
It is called "Text".
It's very similar to String.
And you can also use notation like this, but
you also need to use the "pack" function.
And if you have looked at the examples or
the templates for the last exercise we gave,
you can see this in action.
So, if you want to use strings or character
sequences in CodeWorld, then do it in the
same way it was done in the previous exercise
week.
From there, use the examples for how this
is done.
And then, there's another way to combine or
arrange values in a more complex structure.
Besides lists, there are tuple types.
But the difference with them is that, on the
one hand, they don't have to be homogeneous.
So, you can have a pair of integers or a triple
of integers, strings, and Booleans.
So, it doesn't have to be homogeneous, but
with a fixed length.
If you have a triple type, then all values
of the type must be triples.
You can't, like in a list type, have several
lists of different lengths, for example.
So list types are homogeneous and a list value
can be arbitrarily long.
Tuple types are not homogeneous: You can have
triples of different types as ingredients,
but every element of this type has to be a
triple.
You can't have a type which contains some
pairs and some triples, for example.
And all these constructs can be combined.
So, you can have lists of pairs, pairs of lists,
lists of pairs of lists and pairs.
You can nest basic types at all places.
And of course, later on, when we define our
own datatypes, they can also be used in lists
and tuples, etc.
So, there is a combinatorial domain of type
constructors and you can combine them in many
different ways.
And already with the basic things that you
see on this slide, you have quite a few choices
to arrange your data.
And to illustrate this, I will show some values
of some of these types in a separate whiteboard
video.